Thus far in our application we loaded the single post route as part of our blog page so that when we
imdiye dek uygulamanzda, blog sayfamzn bir paras olarak tek posta yolu yklediimizden, bir
click on a post, we exchanged the posts page for the single post page.
postaya tkladmzda, Postun sayfasn tek bir posta sayfas ile deitirdik.
Now we can absolutely do that of course,
imdi elbette bunu kesinlikle yapabiliriz.
however sometimes you also have a set up where you want to create a nested route. So where you want to
Bununla birlikte, bazen, i ie gemi bir yol oluturmak istediiniz belirli bir bileene sahipseniz
load a certain component or where you want to render certain content inside of another component which
veya belirli bir bileeni yklemek istiyorsanz veya ayn zamanda ynlendirme yoluyla yklenen baka bir bileenin iinde
is also loaded via routing.
belirli ierii oluturmak istiyorsanz.
So right now we have only one level where we do routing, here in the blog container we load different
Dolaysyla u anda burada sadece bir seviye var, burada blok konteynerde ynlendirme yapmaktayz, farkl
components for different routes and that's absolutely fine.
rotalar iin farkl bileenler yklyoruz ve bu kesinlikle iyi.
Now let's say we want to load a specific host not inside the blog component but inside the post component
imdi, blok bileeni iinde deil, burada yaynlarmzn hemen altndaki ana makine bileeninde belirli bir ana
right beneath our posts here.
makine yklemek istediimizi sylemeyelim.
So for that I will wrap this in a div and add my route in there, my route component in there, so now, I'm
Bunun iin bunu Dith'e yapacam ve oraya rota ekleyeceim, orada rota bileenimi orada
in the post component added there.
eklenen post bileeni iinde.
Therefore of course, I also need to add an import at the top where I import route from react-router-dom
Dolaysyla elbette post-bileeninin hepsinde yeniden ynlendirici ynlendiriciden rotay ieri aktardm stte bir ie
all of that in the post component and I now get an error of course because the full post component
aktarma eklemem gerekiyor ve imdi burada bir hatayla karlayorum nk burada atfta bulunulan tam yaz
I'm referring to here is also not present in that file.
bileeni Bu dosyada da mevcut deildir.
So I need to add an import to that too. import FullPost from
Bu yzden, tam postay ieri aktarmak iin bunun iin bir ie aktarma eklemeliyim.
and now let's go to that full post folder and import it from the full post file.
Ve imdi tam deftere nakil klasrne gidelim ve tam posta dosyasndan ie aktaralm.
And now I can render a single post beneath my list of posts because I use route in a different component
Ve imdi, rota listemi farkl bir bileenden kullandmdan tek bir yayn yapabilirim, nk bu genel olarak
and this is in general something you can of course do.
tabii ki yapabileceiniz bir ey.
You can use the route component where ever you want in your application
Uygulamanzda istediin yerde rota bileenini kullanabilirsiniz.
as long as the page the component where you are using it is wrapped by that browser router and that
Sayfay kullandnz bileen, tarayc ynlendiricisi tarafndan sktrld srece elbette durum
of course is the case because we're wrapping the blog component with it.
budur nk blok bileenini onunla saryoruz.
and since the post component is just a child component of the blog component loaded through a route,
Posta bileeni, bir rota zerinden yklenen blok bileenlerinin sadece bir alt
this works.
bileenidir nk bu alr.
Now the switch statement here in the blog component of course is a bit redundant
imdi burada block bileeni switch ifadesi biraz gereksiz.
now, I only have one component in there so maybe I move my outer route in there though technically this
imdi orada sadece bir bileen var, belki de teknik olarak bu zorunlu deildir, nk bu iki
is not required because these two routes will never match for the same path.
rota ayn yol iin asla elemeyecek, ancak d rotam oraya tadm.
So we could remove the switch statement, I'll leave it here simply as a reference so that you can still
Dolaysyla switch ifadesini kaldrabiliriz, bylece burada kodunuzu bir araya getirebilmeniz iin
compare your code to it.
yalnzca bir referans olarak brakrz.
What we can also do in the blog component now is we can get rid of the full post import which we're
Blok bileeninde imdi yapabileceimiz ey, artk burada kullanmadmz tam post ie
not using here anymore.
aktarma ileminden kurtulabilmemiz.
Now if you save all the files and you go to your post component and you click on a single post, you will
kaydedip post bileenine giderseniz tek bir mesaj tklarsanz gncellemeler olduunuzu greceksiniz.
see that URL updates
imdi tm dosyalar
but the post isn't rendered and the posts are gone too.
Ancak grev sonras deil ve yaynlar da gitti.
The reason for this is that we now create a nested route,
Bunun nedeni imdi i ie gemi bir rota oluturmamz.
we have the root route let's say here in the blog container, this is the top most level where we react
Blok konteynrnda burada syleyelim rota yolumuz var, herhangi bir rota deiikliine tepki verdiimiz en
to any route changes, and then the post component which we load through a router.
st seviye ve ardndan bir ynlendiriciden yklediimiz posta bileeni yok.
Keep that in mind we load it,
Bunu unutmayn ki ykledik.
we implement it through the router in this component here.
Bu bileendeki ynlendirici araclyla burada uyguladk.
We now again use route,
imdi yine rota kullanyoruz.
the issue is for /someID,
Sorun, Slash iin bir kimlik belgesi.
We're not going to reach that route because we have the exact matching for just slash. So slash ID doesn't
Bu rotaya ulaamayacaz nk tam eleme yapmamz iin sadece eik izgi Kimliimiz o
match that route,
rotayla uyumuyor.
so the post component never gets rendered which is too bad because it would be in that component that
Dolaysyla, Post bileeni, belirli bir kimlik iin tam yaz
we want to render our full post component for a given ID.
bileenini oluturmak istediimiz bileende olaca iin ok kt hale getirilmez.
Now to fix this we can of course remove exact then this will match slash and /1, /2 and
imdi bunu dzeltmek iin elbette exect'i kaldrabiliriz, bu durumda bu eik izgi ile eleecek ve iki eik izgi
so on.
ikiye blnecektir.
We should then change the order though so that slash doesn't also consume the new posts first and
ancak eik izgi yeni yayn ilk nce bulunursa bu olacak sonra ynlendirici bundan sonra duracaktr.
now switch also makes sense again because now, this route would also be rendered for a /new-post
Sonra sipariiniz deitirilmeliydi, bylece eik izgi ilk nce yeni yaynlar tketmiyor ve imdi mantkl
but since /new-post is found first, this will be rendered first and the router will then stop thereafter.
da oluyor, nk imdi bu rota eik izgi iin yeni bir yayn iin oluturulmu olacak,
So now with this set up you will see that indeed we can load a single route beneath our routes.
imdi bu kurulumla, rotalarmzn altnda tek bir rota ykleyebildiimizi greceksiniz.
So if I go to just slash, we see just the posts but if I click on a post we load that beneath the posts.
Dolaysyla sadece eik izgiye gidersem sadece yazlar grrsem, ancak bir yaz zerine tklarsam yazlarn altna yklenir.
This already is a nested route.
Bu zaten i ie gemi bir yoldur.
We face an issue though, let's say we have /posts here and not slash nothing
Buna ramen, burada Slash mesajlarmz var ve hibir eyi kesmemeliyiz diyebiliriz.
and of course this means that in the post component where we navigate, if we were to use a link we would
Ve tabii ki bunun anlam, bir balant kullansaydk dolatmz post bileenlerinde, postalar kesmek iin bunu
have to update this to /posts.
gncellemek zorunda kalacamz anlamna gelir.
The same here for this programmatic routing and for the one we're actually using
Ayn ey, bu programl ynlendirme ve aslnda kullandmz ynlendirme iin de ayn.
so that now we're navigating to /posts ID. And now with this in place, you will see and I should also
Dolaysyla imdi, posta kutusu kimliini izmek iin geziniyoruz ve eer bu yerinde grrseniz ve
update the navigational link here to /posts
buradaki balantlar buradaki kprleme gnl iin de gncellemeliyiz.
so now you will see that if I click on posts here, we load the posts and I can click on a post of course.
imdi greceksiniz ki buradaki mesajlara tklarsam yazlar ykleyeceim ve elbette bir yazy tklayabilirim.
Now you see also that it fails though, we get an error because our nested route here in the post component,
imdi hepsini baarsz gryorsunuz, nk bir hata aldk, nk burada posttaki i ie gemi rota bileen.
this route, parses /ID and this is not appended to the path of the route which was responsible for
Bu yol eik izgi kimliini ayrtryor ve bu, posta bileeni yklemekten sorumlu olan rota
loading the post component.
yoluna eklenmiyor.
So this is not automatically resolved
Dolaysyla bu otomatik olarak zlmez.
to posts ID,
ki mesaj kimlii.
this is not happening.
Bu gereklemiyor.
Instead this still is /route /ID. So we would have to update this to /posts:id too, to have
Bunun yerine hala eik izgi eik izgi kimliidir; bu nedenle, bunu, yeni oluturduumuz yuvalanm ynlendirme yapmak iin, kimlik dorulama ktn
working nested routing again with our new URL which is /posts /id
blmlere ayracak bir gncelletirme yapmak zorunda kalacaz. Bu, eik izgi eik izgi olan l'dir.
is of course very cumbersome to do so.
Kimliin elbette bunu yapmak ok hantaldr.
So instead of using post like this,
Yani bunun yerine yaz kullanmak yerine.
a better way is to get the current path dynamically so that this really is a dynamic, a flexible nested
Daha iyi bir yol, mevcut yolu dinamik olarak elde etmektir; bylece bu, dinamik, esnek bir i ie gemi rota olur ve
route and for that path should be set to something dynamic here not a hardcoded string.
bu pauvres iin burada sabit kodlanm bir dize deil dinamik bir ey olarak ayarlanmaldr.
And in there, we probably should use this.props.match this match object and in there there is a URL
Ve sonra muhtemelen bu pervanenin eleme uyumazl nesnesini kullanmal ve orada temel olarak D veya l
property which is basically the URL
olan bir u r l zellii var.
we loaded thus far.
imdiye kadar ykledik.
So the URL which was responsible for loading this posts component and that of course is exactly the path
Bu yaz bileenlerini yklemekten sorumlu olan ddktr ve tabii ki yola kmak haricinde.
we need to prepend to our flexible path thereafter. So we can now merge this inside of the curly braces
Esnek blmmz oradan sonra eklemeliyiz, bylece bunu Cauley parantezleri iinde
though with our ID,
kimliklerimizle de birletirebiliriz.
so with /:id and remove the path after the curly braces.
Bylece Slash kolon kimlii ile ve parantez aramak iin para teklif kaldrn.
Now this will match.posts.id and if we ever were to load this component differently, let's say on /
tm yaynlar eik izgi zerine yazarsak dinamik olduu iin bu yaz otomatik olarak tm yaynlara zmlenecektir.
allposts, then this would automatically resolve to all posts here because it is dynamic.
imdi bu, yayn kimliiyle eleecek ve eer bu bileeni farkl ykleyecek olsaydk,
So now with that, if we save this, we get the same behavior as before but this just proves that it's working.
imdi bunu kaydettiimizde, bunu kurtarrsak, daha nce olduu gibi davranrz, ancak bu sadece onun altn kantlyor.
We're dynamically adding /posts here for our nested route and this is how you create truly nested
Yuvalanm rotamza dinamik olarak eik izgi ilanlar ekliyoruz ve yeniden hareket ettiren rvanyla yeniden uygulama
routes in your react application with react router.
uygulamanzda gerekten yuvalanm rotalar oluturduunuz ekilde.